Build a second brain with Obsidian and AI.
The $0 system that changed everything.
Hook.
$0100 to $030.
I was drowning in 847 open browser tabs.
12 half finished notes apps.
And a notion workspace so bloated it took eight seconds to load.
Then I build a second brain using Obsidian and Free AI plugins.
Total cost.
$0.
Result.
I remember everything.
Write 3x faster.
And never lose an idea again.
And I am going to show you exactly how to build yours in the next ten minutes.
Content.
Section 1.
What is a second brain and why most people build it wrong?
A second brain is not a fancy note-taking system.
It is an externalized memory that thinks like you do.
Most people fail because they try to organize notes into folders before they understand
their own.
Thinking patterns.
Chiago Forte's paramethid works.
But only if you adapt it.
I use a modified version.
Projects.
Knowledge.
AI generated.
And archive.
It lives entirely inside Obsidian.
Sync for free via GitHub.
And augmented by two AI plugins that cost nothing.
Section 2.
Obsidian setup.
The free foundation.
Obsidian is free for personal use and runs locally.
No subscription.
No cloud dependency.
No vendor lock in.
First, install these community plugins.
Data view for dynamic note dashboards.
Templator for automatic metadata injection.
And Obsidian Git for free version backup to GitHub.
Your vault structure should be flat.
One folder per project.
One folder for sources.
And everything else link via tags and backlinks.
The magic is not the folders.
It is the connections between ideas.
Section 3.
The AI plugins that turn notes into intelligence.
Here is where it gets unfair.
Install the smart connections plugin.
It embeds every note into a vector space locally.
Zero API calls.
Pro cost.
And surfaces related ideas you forgot you wrote.
Then add local images plus to have AI describe your screenshots and diagrams automatically
using.
Local vision models.
The result?
You type client-pitch stress points and your second brain surfaces every related meeting
note.
Book highlight.
And random thought from the past two years.
It feels like having a research assistant who has read your entire mind.
Section 4.
The daily workflow.
Takes 7 minutes.
Morning.
I dump every thought into a daily note using voice to text on my phone.
Midday.
I run smart connections to see which past notes relate to today's problems evening.
I tag three notes for AI summarization and move finished project notes to archive.
The entire system runs offline.
No cloud AI required.
No subscription.
Just a free app and a discipline 7 minute habit.
Section 5.
Real results after 90 days.
Before this system, I rewrote the same introductions three times because I forgot where
I saved the first draft.
Now I have a searchable library of 2,400 ideas.
87 book summaries.
And 145 client call insights.
My article output went from 2 per month to 6.
My anxiety about forgetting things disappeared.
The system is not sexy.
It is invisible.
That is the point.
Call to action.
Final 30s.
If you want the exact vault template I use.
It is linked in the description.
It is free.
Open source.
And takes 3 minutes to import.
Subscribe if you want more zero dollar productivity systems that actually work.
And tell me in the comments.
What is the one idea or note you have lost three times because you could not find it?
I will reply with a tagging strategy to fix it.