chat gpt vs clawed vs deep seek vs kimi
the winner will shock you
hook
0-030
i ran the same 10 prompts through chat gpt
clawed
deep seek
and kimi
one model made me delete the other three
and the winner is not the one you think
if you are paying $200 a month for the wrong tool
this video will save you money and make you smarter
content
section one the test nobody does
every comparison video online uses cherry-picked examples from model press releases
i did something different i gave each model a $500 freelance coding task
a creative writing brief a math Olympiad problem
and a negotiation simulation
then i blind-ranked the outputs before checking which model wrote what
the results were humbling
section two chat gpt
the safe default that costs too much
chat gpt is the iPhone of AI
it works
it is polished
and it rarely surprises you
but that is also the problem
open AI has sanitized it so aggressively that it feels like talking to a corporate lawyer who
learned empathy from a TED talk
on the coding task it produced working code instantly
but refused to optimize it because the prompt might be used for scraping
that hesitation cost it
the win
when you are paying $20 to $200 a month
you want a tool that trusts you
not one that parent scolds you
section three
clawed
the writer's secret weapon
clawed wrote the best first draft of the creative brief
the pros had rhythm
the structure had logic
and the personality felt human
but clawed choked on the math problem
not a little
it confidently delivered the wrong answer
and then wrote three paragraphs defending the wrong
answer using fake citations
this is the sophisticated hallucination problem
if you write novels or marketing copy
clawed is unmatched
if you need facts
it is dangerous
section four
deep seek
the underdog that punches above its weight
deep seek is free
fast
and uncensored
it optimized the code without asking permission
solve the math problem correctly
and negotiate it like a shark
so why is it not the winner
because the interface is clunky
the context window resets randomly
and the web search feature is buried under three menus
freed is not beat usable
but if you are technical enough to work around the friction
deep seek is secretly the best value on the planet
section five
chemi
the surprise winner
chemi handled every task with the confidence of a specialist
who actually enjoys the work
the code was clean and commented
the math was correct and explained step by step
the negotiation simulation adapted to my counter offers in real time
and the writing
it was not as poetic as clawed
but it was accurate, structured
and honest about uncertainty
that honesty matters more than flair
when you are building a business
or debugging a failing product
section six
the cost reality check
chat gpt plus
$20 per month
clawed pro
deep seek
free but costs time
chemi
free tier available
paid tier competitive
here is the brutal truth
the best model is the one that does your specific job best writers should use clawed
coders should use chemi
rebels and hackers should use deep seek
chat gpt is the safe middle
and in AI
safe middle means you are paying a premium for average
call to action
final 30s
if this video saved you from wasting money
hit subscribe
i test AI tools so you do not have to
drop a comment telling me which model you are married to right now and whether this video changed
your mind
next week
i am pitting these same four models against each other in a 24 hour startup challenge
and one of them is building an actual profitable product
you will not believe which one