I replaced five paid apps with open source.
Here's my exact stack.
Hook.
0100-030.
I was bleeding $147 every single month on software subscriptions.
Notion.
One password.
Figma.
To-do-ist.
Lightroom.
All solid tools.
But my credit card was screaming.
Then I went nuclear.
I wiped the slate clean and rebuilt my entire productivity stack.
Using only open source software.
Same output.
Zero licensing fees.
And honestly, some of these free tools run circles around the paid versions I left behind.
Here's the exact five app swap that saved me nearly two grand a year.
Content.
Section 1.
Notion-right-pointing-arrow log seek.
The second brain that actually belongs to you.
I used to treat notion like my external brain.
Every article draft.
Project timeline.
And random shower thought lived inside those glossy little blocks.
Until the day I was on a four hour flight with no Wi-Fi and needed to access my content
calendar.
I opened Notion.
I stared at a spinning wheel for 20 minutes.
That was the moment I realized I wasn't building a second brain.
I was renting storage in someone else's warehouse.
And the landlord had just changed the locks.
Switching to log seek felt like moving from a furnished apartment into a house I actually
owned.
It's an open source.
Local first knowledge graph that stores everything in plain markdown files on your actual hard
drive.
I recreated my entire content pipeline using daily journals.
Link references.
And simple page properties.
Now, when I tag a video idea with script pending, it automatically surfaces in my weekly
review query.
The graph view even showed me connections between topics I didn't realize were related.
Something Notions rigid hierarchy never revealed.
I sink it to my private get repository for backup.
Which costs me nothing.
Best part?
During another flight.
Same laptop.
Zero internet.
I pulled up log seek and kept working seamlessly.
My thoughts.
My files.
My machine.
That's the difference between borrowing and owning your ideas.
Section 2 to 1 password right pointing arrow bitwarden.
Your keys.
Your kingdom.
Password managers are supposed to be vaults.
But most people are storing their gold in a safety deposit box where the bank controls
the key.
When last pass had its catastrophic breach, I looked at my one password subscription and
felt a familiar itch.
What if the next headline was theirs?
Exporting my data felt intentionally clunky.
Like a gym making cancellation harder than sign up.
That's not security.
That's custody.
Bitwarden is fully open source.
Which means its code is audited by thousands of eyes worldwide.
I migrated 300 passwords.
Credit cards.
And secure notes in under an hour using a simple CSV import.
The mobile app syncs instantly and the biometric unlock is smoother than one password was on
my phone.
For most users, the free tier is genuinely enough.
Unlimited passwords across unlimited devices.
But I went a step further and spun up vaultwarden.
A lightweight self-hosted fork.
On a cheap home server.
Now my encrypted vault lives on hardware I control.
The browser extension auto fills faster than one password ever did.
And the built-in TOTP generator means I don't need a separate authenticator app.
It's like building your own panic room.
You still get bank rate encryption.
But you hold the only key.
In three, Figma write pointing arrow penpot.
Design without the paywall.
Figma is the industry standard for a reason.
But industry standards love to move the goalposts.
When they locked developer handoff and advanced prototyping behind a higher paywall last year.
My monthly bill for two designer seats jump overnight.
It reminded me of a carpenter who builds an entire workshop inside someone else's garage.
Then wakes up to find the rent doubled and the power tools chained up.
Penpot is the open source design platform that runs entirely in your browser.
Just like Figma, but with zero strings attached.
Because it's built on SVG standards.
Every shape, board, and component you create is native web code.
Not a proprietary blob.
I rebuilt my entire YouTube thumbnail system inside Penpot in a weekend.
The Flex Layout system actually handles responsive design better than Figma's constraints.
And sharing a prototype with a freelancer is as simple as sending a URL.
No seat limits.
No dev mode upsell.
If Penpot ever disappears.
I still own every SVG file.
Try saying that about a Figma design locked in the cloud.
The learning curve is about 48 hours.
The freedom is permanent.
Section 4.
To doist right-pointing arrow super productivity.
Pasks on steroids.
To doist is beautiful.
But it's also a masterclass in the productivity tax.
Charging you subscription fees for features that should be table stakes.
I remember missing a client deadline because to doist hid the reminder behind a premium
badge.
Even buying a car and discovering the brakes are part of a DLC pack.
That's when I started hunting for a task manager that respects both my time and my wallet.
Super productivity is an open source desktop app that looks simple until you realize it's
a...
Pactical Command Center.
The keyboard shortcuts alone saved me more time in a week than to doist did in a month.
I used it to produce this very video.
I broke the script into subtasks.
Assigned time estimates.
And used the built-in Pomodoro timer to stay honest during writing sessions.
When I dragged a task onto the calendar view, it automatically blocked out research time
and flagged conflicts with my recording schedule.
It even tracks how long I actually spend versus what I predicted.
So my estimates get sharper every week.
There are no artificial caps on projects.
No paywalls on notifications.
And no cloud required.
It lives on your machine.
Starts in under a second.
And treats you like a power user from day one.
Section 5.
Adobe Lightroom Right Pointing Arrow Darktable.
Raw Power.
Zero Rent.
Adobe's photography ecosystem is a velvet trap.
They hook you with student pricing.
Unslowly crank the subscription dial while your entire photo library gets glued to their
cloud.
Last year, my creative cloud bill crossed $200 annually just for Lightroom and Photoshop.
I had 50,000 raw photos.
Essentially my visual memory.
Locked inside an ecosystem that could change pricing.
Terms.
Or access whenever they wanted.
Just like developing photos in a darkroom where the landlord can walk in and turn off
the safe lights.
Darktable is the open source raw processor that professional photographers secretly swear
by.
I imported my entire four terabytes Sony A7IV image archive in one evening.
The filmic RGB module gives me color grading control that rivals Lightroom's developed
panel.
And every single edit is saved as a sidecar file next to the original raw.
That means if I uninstall Darktable tomorrow.
My edits are still readable, portable, and mine.
I build a custom preset stack for my YouTube thumbnails so every photo starts with the
same.
Baseline contrast and skin tone protection.
No monthly fee.
No cloud upload bottleneck.
First raw processing power that respects the fact that your portfolio is a lifetime asset.
Not a rental.
Call to action.
Final 30s.
Here's the truth nobody tells you.
Open source isn't about suffering through clunky software to save a few bucks.
It's about ownership.
When you control your tools.
You control your workflow.
Your data.
And your monthly budget.
If you want me to do a deep dive setup tutorial on any of these five apps.
Drop the name in the comments.
And if you're still on the fence about one.
Tell me which paid tool you're most scared to lose.
I'll reply with a migration battle plan that covers export.
Import.
And the first week of habit adjustment.
See you in the next one.