7 Productivity Tools The Guru's Hide Because They Worked To Well
Hook.
0100-030.
I spent $2,400 last year on Productivity courses.
Planners.
Enapse that promise to 10X My Output.
The Secret The Guru's Never Tell You?
The Best Tools Are Free.
Open Source.
And Intentionally Hard to Find Because Nobody Makes Affiliate Commissions From Them.
I am Exposing All 7.
Two of them are so effective I considered keeping them private.
Content.
Section 1.
Tool Number 1.
The Free Focus Timer That Beats Every Paid App.
The tool is called Engage Timer.
It is a browser extension with zero tracking.
Zero ads.
And a brutal accountability feature.
If you leave the tab, it automatically pauses and tweets your failure.
Optionally, To a Private Accountability Group.
Unlike Forrest or Focus At Will.
There is no gamified nonsense.
Just a timer.
A Commitment.
And Consequences.
I went from 47 minutes of average deep work to 2 hours and 12 minutes in the first week.
The Difference Was Not The Tool.
It Was The Loss A Version Build Into The Design.
Section 2.
Tool Number 2.
The Read Later App With Built-In AI Summarization.
Omnivore Is Free.
Open Source.
And Has a Killer Feature.
Every article you save gets automatically summarized by a local LLM.
You own your data.
Your highlights export to Obsidian in one click.
The Reading Experience Is Cleaner Than Pocket.
And the AI Summaries Are Accurate Enough That I Now Read 12 Articles per Day Instead of
Three.
The gurus Do Not Promote It Because There Is No Referral Program.
Section 3.
Tool Number 3.
The Email Client That Ends Inbox Zero Forever.
Nile Is Mail Is Not An Email Client.
It Is An Email Operating System.
It Auto-Sorts Emails By Sender Importance Using On Device AI.
Drafts Replies In Your Voice.
And Surfaces Only The Five Emails That Actually Need Your Human Brain.
I Check Email Once per Day Now.
Before Nile Is.
I Checked 47 Times.
The Math Is Embarrassing.
And It Is Completely Free For Personal Use.
Section 4.
Tool Number 4.
The Clipboard Manager With A Memory.
Ditto On Windows And McKee On Mac Remember Everything You Copy.
For Years.
I Have 34,000 Clipboard Entries Archived.
When a client asks for, that link I sent three months ago, I search three keywords and
find it in.
Four Seconds.
It Sounds Trivial Until You Realize How Much Time You Waste Refinding Things You Already
Found.
Section 5.
Tool Number 5.
The Free AI That Rites Your Meeting Notes.
Fireflies.AI has a free tier that transcribes and summarizes unlimited meetings.
But here is the secret.
Parit with a free local LLM via API and the summaries become action items with owners
and.
Deadlines Automatically Extracted.
The paid version charges $19 per month for this.
The free version does 90% of it with a 10 line script.
Section 6.
Tool Number 6.
The Browser That Block's Distractions At The DNS Level.
Brave Browser With Custom Filter Lists blocks not just ads.
But entire categories of distracting sites at the DNS level.
I have a Work Mode List That Makes Reddit.
X.
And YouTube Literally Unreachable During Focus Blocks.
No Willpower Required.
No Extension Juggling.
The Sites Do Not Resolve.
Period.
Section 7.
Tool Number 7.
The To-Do App That Tracks Your Real Capacity.
Sunsama has a free tier that forces you to estimate task duration.
Then Realistically Caps Your Daily Plan Based On Historical Completion Rates.
It Learned I Overestimate My Capacity By 40%.
Now at Auto Adjusts.
I Finish My List Every Day Instead Of Carrying 12 Undone Tasks Into Tomorrow.
The Psychological Relief Is Worth More Than The Productivity Gain.
Call to Action.
Final 30s.
All 7 Tools Are Linked In The Description With Setup Guides.
If this video saves you from buying another $297 Productivity Course.
Hit Subscribe.
I Only Share Tools That Are Free.
Field Tested.
And Actually Used In My Daily Workflow.
Comment Below With The Tool That Shocked You Most.
Or Tell Me The Paid App You Are Finally Ready To Cancel.