Why eye productivity is secretly destroying your career.
My 90-day experiment.
Hook.
0100-030.
I outsourced my entire job to chat GPT for 90 days.
My output tripled.
My boss loved me.
And I almost got fired anyway.
Because eye productivity has a dark side that nobody in the tech bro community wants to admit.
Using these tools for everything doesn't just make you dependent.
It quietly erases the exact skills that make you hireable,
promotable, and creatively dangerous in the first place.
And by the end of this story, you'll understand why the smartest people I know are now intentionally using AI less.
Not more.
Content.
Section 1.
The GPS Effect.
Cognitive Atrophy.
She's a marketing manager who decided to automate every cognitive task she possibly could.
Chat GPT wrote her emails.
It brainstormed her campaigns.
It drafted her Slack updates and even generated her performance reviews.
For six months, she was the most efficient person in her department.
Her manager praised her turnaround time.
Then one Monday morning, the company Wi-Fi went down during a critical product launch.
Sarah sat in front of a blank word document for 45 minutes.
Unable to write a simple two-page creative brief without an AI crutch.
She hadn't lost her job.
She had lost her ability to think from first principles.
Neuroscientists have a term for this.
They call it the GPS Effect.
When you use turn-by-turn navigation for every single drive, your hippocampus physically shrinks
because your brain stops building cognitive maps.
AI is doing the exact same thing to your prefrontal cortex.
Every time you outsource your thinking to a chatbot, you're telling your brain that forming ideas independently is optional.
An optional muscles atrophy fast the scary part?
You don't notice it happening until the Wi-Fi cuts out.
Or until your boss asks a strategic question that isn't in the AI's training data.
By then, your mental map is already gone.
And rebuilding it takes 10 times longer than you expect because you have to relearn how to sit.
With uncertainty, Section 2, the competence trap.
Then there's Alex, junior developer, Bright Guy,
started using GitHub Copilot for practically every line of code.
He was shipping tickets three times faster than the senior engineers.
Management promoted him within eight months.
Then, during a critical site outage at 2 a.m., the AI service was down.
Alex opened the codebase and panicked.
He couldn't debug a basic Python loop without autocomplete suggestions.
The skills he thought he had were just a reflection of the algorithm holding his hand.
Researchers at Stanford ran a controlled study on this exact phenomenon.
Programmers who used AI assistance for their daily work scored 40% lower on manual coding.
Assessments six months later.
But here's the kicker.
They rated their own abilities significantly higher than coders who worked alone.
It's done in Kruger Fueled by Silicon.
Think of it like a pilot who logs 10,000 hours of flight time.
But 9,000 of them are on autopilot.
When the storm hits and the screens go dark, he doesn't know how to read the instruments.
If your entire workflow is AI assisted, you aren't building expertise.
You're curating it, and curated competence shatters the moment the API times out.
Or when a client asks you to explain the underlying logic you supposedly wrote.
The tool becomes a crutch.
And crutches don't make your legs stronger.
They just make you forget you ever walked without them.
Section 3. The Shadow workload.
Mike is a consultant who bragged about his $500 a month AI stack.
He had auto transcribing his meetings.
Notion AI summarizing his notes.
Claude drafting his proposals.
And mid-journey generating his slide decks.
On paper.
He was saving 10 hours a week.
In reality, he was spending six hours managing prompts.
Fixing AI hallucinations.
Copy pasting between platforms.
And triple checking research because the model cited three studies that didn't exist economists.
Call this the Shadow workload.
Tasks that are created by the very tools designed to eliminate tasks.
It's like buying a robot to wash your dishes.
But you spend all day repairing the robot.
Pre-rinsing its mistakes.
And washing the same plate twice because the robot missed a spot.
The productivity industry won't show you this math.
They sell you the dream of frictionless output.
But every AI tool adds a new layer of friction disguised as automation.
The real cost isn't the monthly subscription fee.
It's the cognitive switching tax of jumping between seven AI assistants.
The decision fatigue of choosing which bot to use for which sentence.
And the slow erosion of trust in your own deliverables.
You don't become more productive.
You become an anxious editor of machine guesses instead of an author of human ideas.
That identity shift is subtle.
But it is absolutely corrosive to long-term mastery.
Section 4. The Commodization Cliff.
Emma was a copier-writer who used AI to 10X her output.
She could knock out 30 blog posts in a day.
Her clients loved the speed and the discounted rates.
Then her biggest clients send an email that stopped her cold.
If you're just prompting AI and light editing the output.
Why am I paying you $3,000 a month instead of $20 for the tool myself?
Emma had no answer.
She had spent a year outsourcing her taste.
Her voice.
And her strategic thinking to a model.
The skills that once made her irreplaceable had become a commodity.
There's a rule in economics called the Commodization Trap.
When a tool makes a skill scalable.
It also makes the human behind it replaceable.
Think of it like a chef who only reheats microwave meals.
Eventually, the restaurant realizes it doesn't need the chef.
Just the microwave.
If your entire value proposition is that you can operate AI faster than your client can.
You aren't selling expertise.
You're selling access.
And access always gets undercut by cheaper technology.
Hungry or freelancers.
Or eventually.
The client's own teenage kid who learns the same prompt you use.
The moment your work becomes indistinguishable from pure AI output.
You have priced yourself out of relevance.
And recovery is brutal.
Section 5. The antidote.
Strategic friction.
So what's the fix?
I watched a product lead at a Fintech company implement what he called strategic friction.
He. Bandai for first draft thinking entirely.
Every morning.
He spent 30 minutes with a pen and paper.
Mapping out strategy.
Writing outlines.
And wrestling with problems before touching a keyboard.
Only after he had formed his own clear thesis did he open chat GPT.
And solely to edit.
Format.
Or stress test his logic.
His output dropped by 20%.
His originality and accuracy skyrocketed.
Six months later.
He was the only person on his team who could articulate why their AI driven competitors were making.
A catastrophic pricing mistake.
He saw the blind spot because he had trained his brain to think.
Not just to prompt.
Think of AI like a set of weighted plates that an athlete trains with.
You don't wear the weights during the game.
You wear them during practice so that on game day.
Without the weights.
You explode past everyone else.
AI should be your game day boost.
Not your permanent training wheels.
The most dangerous thing you can do is forget how to run without them.
Use AI to amplify clarity.
Not to replace the hard work of forming it.
Call to action.
Final 30s.
Your brain is the only truly irreplaceable asset you own.
Before you outsource your next big decision to a chatbot.
Ask yourself whether you're building a skill or just renting one for convenience.
If you want more contrarian takes on AI.
Real productivity.
And tools that actually respect your intelligence rather than replacing it.
Subscribe and hit the notification bell.
I drop one video a week that your AI assistant definitely didn't write.
I'll see you in the next one.